window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - Verbal_Ability_–_CSE",
  "duration": 302,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Verbal_Ability_–_CSE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The diagram below shows a river system consisting of 7 segments, marked P, Q, R, S, T, U, and V. It splits the land into 5 zones, marked Z1, Z2, Z3, Z4, and Z5. We need to connect these zones using the least number of bridges. Out of the following options, which one is correct? <br>Note: The figure shown is representative. <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q65_9c4479d6.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, and T</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, S, and T</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Bridges on Q, R, T, and V</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, S, U, and V</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Bridges on Q, R, T, and V</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460441/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Based only on the conversation below, identify the logically correct inference:  <br><br>\n\"Even if I had known that you were in the hospital, I would not have gone there to see you\", Ramya told Josephine. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Ramya knew that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Ramya did not know that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Ramya and Josephine were once close friends; but now, they are not.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Josephine was in the hospital due to an injury to her leg.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Ramya did not know that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460445/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The paper as shown in the figure is folded to make a cube where each square corresponds to a particular face of the cube. Which one of the following options correctly represents the cube?<br>Note: The figures shown are representative.  <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q59a_bbf0880b.webp\"><br><br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q59b_37c3fe6d.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>B</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>C</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>D</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460447/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Bird : Nest :: Bee : __________   <br> Select the correct option to complete the analogy. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Kennel</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Hammock</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Hive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Lair</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Hive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460449/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Despite his initial hesitation, Rehman's __________ to contribute to the success of the project never wavered. <br>Select the most appropriate option to complete the above sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>ambivalence</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>satisfaction</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>resolve</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>revolve</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>resolve</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460450/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A square paper, shown in figure (I), is folded along the dotted lines as shown in the figures (II) and (III). Then a few cuts are made as shown in figure (IV). Which one of the following patterns will be obtained when the paper is unfolded?\n<br>Note: The figures shown are representative.<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q64a_4c00fbae.webp\"><br><br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q64b_b423886b.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>B</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>C</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>D</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460092/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>\"I put the brown paper in my pocket along with the chalks, and possibly other things. I suppose everyone must have reflected how primeval and how poetical are the things that one carries in one's pocket: the pocket-knife, for instance the type of all human tools, the infant of the sword. Once I planned to write a book of poems entirely about the things in my pocket. But I found it would be too long: and the age of the great epics is past.\"  <br><br>\n(From G.K. Chesterton's \"A Piece of Chalk\")  <br><br>\nBased only on the information provided in the above passage, which one of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The author of the passage carries a mirror in his pocket to reflect upon things.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The author of the passage had decided to write a poem on epics.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The pocket-knife is described as the infant of the sword.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Epics are described as too inconvenient to write.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The pocket-knife is described as the infant of the sword.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460095/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>According to the map shown in the figure, which one of the following statements is correct?  <br>\nNote: The figure shown is representative. <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q60_d7b5bf82.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The library is located to the northwest of the canteen.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The hospital is located to the east of the chemistry lab.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The classrooms and canteen are next to each other.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460096/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the relationships among P, Q, R, S, and T:  <br><br>\nP is the brother of Q.<br>\nS is the daughter of Q.<br>\nT is the sister of S. <br>\nR is the mother of Q.\n<br><br>\nThe following statements are made based on the relationships given above.<br><br>\nR is the grandmother of S.<br>\nP is the uncle of S and T.<br>\nR has only one son.<br>\nQ has only one daughter.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Both (1) and (3) are true.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (3) is true.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only (4) is true.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460097/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The CEO's decision to downsize the workforce was considered myopic because it sacrificed long-term stability to accommodate short-term gains.  <br>\nSelect the most appropriate option that can replace the word \"myopic\" without changing the meaning of the sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>visionary</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>progressive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>innovative</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460099/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Ravi had _____________ younger brother who taught at _____________ university. He was widely regarded as _____________ honorable man.  <br>\nSelect the option with the correct sequence of articles to fill in the blanks. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the; an; a</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a; an; a</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>an; an; a</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460100/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Sequence the following sentences in a coherent passage.<br><br>\nP:    This fortuitous geological event generated a colossal amount of energy and heat that resulted in the rocks rising to an average height of 4 km across the contact zone.\n<br>Q:    Thus, the geophysicists tend to think of the Himalayas as an active geological event rather than as a static geological feature.\n<br>R:    The natural  process  of  the  cooling  of  this massive  edifice  absorbed  large quantities of atmospheric carbon dioxide, altering the earth?s atmosphere and making it better suited for life.\n<br>S:    Many millennia ago, a breakaway chunk of bedrock from the Antarctic Plate collided with the massive Eurasian Plate. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>QPSR</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>QSPR</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>SRPQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422901/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>If '\\( \\rightarrow \\)' denotes increasing order of intensity, then the meaning of the words\n[walk \\( \\rightarrow \\) jog \\( \\rightarrow \\) sprint] is analogous to [bothered \\( \\rightarrow \\) ________ \\( \\rightarrow \\) daunted].<br>\nWhich one of the given options is appropriate to fill the blank? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>phased</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>phrased</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>fused</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422906/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>In the given text, the blanks are numbered (i)-(iv). Select the best match for all the\nblanks.  <br>\nSteve was advised to keep his head ___(i)___ before heading __(ii)__ to bat;\nfor, while he had a head __(iii)__ batting, he could only do so with a cool head\ns __(iv)__ his shoulders <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) down (iii) on (iv) for</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) on (ii) down (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) out (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(i) on (ii) out (iii) on (iv) for</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) out (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422781/gate-cse-2024-set-1-ga-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If '\\( \\rightarrow \\)' denotes increasing order of intensity, then the meaning of the words\n[dry \\( \\rightarrow \\) arid \\( \\rightarrow \\) parched] is analogous to [diet \\( \\rightarrow \\) fast \\( \\rightarrow \\) _____].\n<br>\nWhich one of the given options is appropriate to fill the blank? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>starve</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>reject</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>feast</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>deny</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>starve</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422786/gate-cse-2024-set-1-ga-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following sentence sequences creates a coherent narrative?<br>\n<br>(i) Once on the terrace, on her way to her small room in the corner, she\nnotices the man right away.\n<br>(ii) She begins to pant by the time she has climbed all the stairs.\n<br>(iii) Mina has bought vegetables and rice at the market, so her bags are\nheavy.\n<br>(iv) He was leaning against the parapet, watching the traffic below. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i), (ii), (iv), (iii)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(ii), (iii), (i), (iv)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(iv), (ii), (i), (iii)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii), (ii), (i), (iv)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii), (ii), (i), (iv)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399248/gate-cse-2023-ga-question8#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>Kind : _______ : : Often : Frequently<br>\n(By word meaning) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mean</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Type</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Cruel</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Kindly</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Type</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399254/gate-cse-2023-ga-question2#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>We reached the station late, and _______ missed the train. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>near</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>nearly</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>utterly</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>mostly</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>nearly</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399255/gate-cse-2023-ga-question1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>The corners and mid-points of the sides of a triangle are named using the distinct letters P, Q, R, S, T and U, but not necessarily in the same order. Consider the following statements:\n<br><br>\nThe line joining P and R is parallel to the line joining Q and S.<br> P is placed on the side opposite to the corner T.\n<br> S and U cannot be placed on the same side.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements is correct based on the above information? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>S cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>U cannot be placed at a mid-point</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R cannot be placed at a corner</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>S cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371497/Gate-cse-2022-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>Some people believe that \"what gets measured, improves\". Some others believe that \"what gets measured, gets gamed\". One possible reason for the difference in the beliefs is the work culture in organizations. In organizations with good work culture, metrics help improve outcomes. However, the same metrics are counterproductive in organizations with poor work culture.\n<br>\nWhich one of the following is the CORRECT logical inference based on the information in the above passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with poor work culture</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with good work culture</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Metrics are always counterproductive in organizations with good work culture</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Metrics are never useful in organizations with good work culture</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with good work culture</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371500/Gate-cse-2022-question-6#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 21,
          "question": "<p>Given below are four statements. <br><br>Statement 1: All students are inquisitive. <br>Statement 2: Some students are inquisitive. <br>Statement 3: No student is inquisitive.\n<br>Statement 4: Some students are not inquisitive.\n<br><br>\nFrom the given four statements, find the two statements that CANNOT BE TRUE simultaneously, assuming that there is at least one student in the class. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Statement 2 and Statement 4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Statement 3 and Statement 4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371502/Gate-cse-2022-question-4#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 22,
          "question": "<p>The _____ is too high for it to be considered ______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fair / fare</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>faer / fair</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fare / fare</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>fare / fair</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>fare / fair</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371505/Gate-cse-2022-ga-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 23,
          "question": "<p>Six students P, Q, R, S, T and U, with distinct heights, compare their heights and make the following observations.<br><br>\nObservation I: S is taller than R.<br>\nObservation II: Q is the shortest of all.<br>\nObservation III: U is taller than only one student.<br>\nObservation IV: T is taller than S but is not the tallest<br><br>\nThe number of students that are taller than R is the same as the number of students shorter than ____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>S</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>S</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357540/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-10#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 24,
          "question": "<p>Listening to music during exercise improves performance and reduces discomfort. Scientists researched whether listening to music while studying can help students learn better and the results were inconclusive. Students who needed external stimulation for studying fared worse while students who did not need any external stimulation benefited from music.<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements is the CORRECT inference of the above passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Listening to music has no effect on learning and a positive effect on physical exercise</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect both in physical exercise and on learning</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on physical exercise. Music has a positive effect on learning only in some students</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on learning in all students. Music has a positive effect only in some students who exercise</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on physical exercise. Music has a positive effect on learning only in some students</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357544/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 25,
          "question": "<p>Pen : Write :: Knife :  _______<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options maintains a similar logical relation in the above? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Vegetables</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Sharp</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Cut</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Blunt</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Cut</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357545/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-5#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 26,
          "question": "<p>Gauri said that she can play the keyboard __________ her sister. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>as well as</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>as better as</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>as nicest as</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>as worse as</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>as well as</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357549/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 27,
          "question": "<p>Some people suggest anti-obesity measures (AOM) such as displaying calorie information in restaurant menus. Such measures sidestep addressing the core problems that cause obesity: poverty and income inequality.<br><br>Which one of the following statements summarizes the passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The proposed AOM addresses the core problems that cause obesity</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If obesity reduces, poverty will naturally reduce, since obesity causes poverty</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the core problems and are likely to succeed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the problem superficially</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the problem superficially</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357467/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-10#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 28,
          "question": "<p>Given below are two statements 1 and 2, and two conclusions I and II<br><br>\nStatement 1: All bacteria are microorganisms.<br>\nStatement 2: All pathogens are microorganisms.<br><br>\nConclusion I: Some pathogens are bacteria.<br>\nConclusion II: All pathogens are not bacteria.<br><br>\nBased on the above statements and conclusions, which one of the following options is logically CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only conclusion I is correct</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only conclusion II is correct</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Either conclusion I or II is correct</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither conclusion I nor II is correct</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither conclusion I nor II is correct</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357468/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 29,
          "question": "<p>There are five bags each containing identical sets of ten distinct chocolates. One chocolate is picked from each bag.\n<br>\nThe probability that at least two chocolates are identical is _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.3024</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.4235</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.6976</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.8125</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.6976</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357469/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-8#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 30,
          "question": "<p>_________ is to surgery as writer is to ___________\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options maintains a similar logical relation in the above sentence? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Plan, outline</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Hospital, library</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Doctor, book</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Medicine, grammar</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Doctor, book</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357472/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-5#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 31,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sentences:\n<br><br>\ni.   Everybody in the class is prepared for the exam.\n<br>ii.  Babu invited Danish to his home because he enjoys playing chess.<br><br>\nWhich of the following is the CORRECT observation about the above two sentences? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is unambiguous</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically incorrect and (ii) is unambiguous</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is ambiguous</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically incorrect and (ii) is ambiguous</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is ambiguous</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357474/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-3#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 32,
          "question": "<p>Goods and Services Tax (GST) is an indirect tax introduced in India in 2017 that is imposed on the supply of goods and services, and it subsumes all indirect taxes except few. It is a destination-based tax imposed on goods and services used, and it is not imposed at the point of origin from where goods come. GST also has a few components specific to state governments, central government  and Union Territories (UTs).<br><br>Which one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>GST is imposed on the production of goods and services.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>GST includes all indirect taxes.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>GST does not have a component specific to UT.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>GST is imposed at the point of usage of goods and services.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>GST is imposed at the point of usage of goods and services.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333235/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 33,
          "question": "<p>The dawn of the 21st century witnessed the melting glaciers oscillating between giving too much and too little to billions of people who depend on them for fresh water. The UN climate report estimates that without deep cuts to man-made emissions, at least 30% of the northern hemisphere's surface permafrost could melt by the end of the century. Given this situation of imminent global exodus of billions of people displaced by rising seas, nation-states need to rethink their carbon footprint for political concerns, if not for environmental ones.<br><br>Which one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Nation-states do not have environmental concerns.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Nation-states are responsible for providing fresh water to billions of people.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Billions of people are responsible foe man-made emissions.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Billions of people are affected by melting glaciers.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Billions of people are affected by melting glaciers.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333237/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 34,
          "question": "<p>Select the word that fits the analogy:\n<br><br>\nCook : Cook :: Fly : _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Flyer</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Flying</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Flew</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Flighter</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Flyer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333238/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 35,
          "question": "<p>His knowledge of the subject was excellent but his classroom performance was_______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>extremely poor</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>good</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>desirable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>praiseworthy</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>extremely poor</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333239/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 36,
          "question": "<p>Raman is confident of speaking English _______six months as he has been practising regularly_______the last three weeks. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>during, for</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>for, since</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>for, in</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>within, for</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>within, for</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333240/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 37,
          "question": "<p>\"A recent High Court judgement has sought to dispel the idea of begging as a disease - which leads to its stigmatization and criminalization  - and to regard it as a symptom. The underlying disease is the failure of the state to protect citizens who fall through the social security net.\"<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Beggars are lazy people who beg because they are unwilling to work</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Beggars are created because of the lack of social welfare schemes</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Begging is an offence that has to be dealt with firmly</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Begging has to be banned because it adversely affects the welfare of the state</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Beggars are created because of the lack of social welfare schemes</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302865/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-8#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 38,
          "question": "<p>A court is to a judge as _________ is to a teacher. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a student</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a punishment</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a syllabus</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a school</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>a school</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302868/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-5#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 39,
          "question": "<p>The search engine's business model ____ around the fulcrum of trust. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>revolves</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>plays</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>sinks</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>bursts</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>revolves</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302871/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 40,
          "question": "<p>The expenditure on the project __________ as follows: equipment Rs.20 lakhs, salaries Rs.12 lakhs, and contingency Rs.3 lakhs. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>break down</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>break</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>breaks down</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>breaks</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>breaks down</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302872/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 41,
          "question": "<p>A ________ investigation can sometimes yield new facts, but typically organized ones are more successful.\n<br><br>\nThe word that best fills the blank in the above sentence is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>meandering</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>timely</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>consistent</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>systematic</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>meandering</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204063/gate-cse-2018-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 42,
          "question": "<p>\"From where are they bringing their books? _______ bringing _______ books from ________\"\n<br><br>\nThe words that best fill the blanks in the above sentence are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Their, they're, there</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>They're, their, there</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There, their, they're</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>They're, there,there</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>They're, their, there</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204062/gate-cse-2018-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 43,
          "question": "<p>\"We lived in a culture that denied any merit to literary works, considering them important only when they were handmaidens to something seemingly more urgent - namely ideology. This was a country where all gestures, even the most private, were interpreted in political terms.\"<br><br>The author's belief that ideology is not as important as literature is revealed by the word: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>culture'</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>seemingly'</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>urgent'</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>political'</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>seemingly'</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118420/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 44,
          "question": "<p>Saturn is ___________ to be seen on a clear night with the naked eye. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>enough bright</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>bright enough</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>as enough bright</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>bright as enough</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>bright enough</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118416/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 45,
          "question": "<p>Choose the option with words that are not synonyms. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>aversion, dislike</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>luminous, radiant</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>plunder, loot</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>yielding, resistant</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>yielding, resistant</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118415/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 46,
          "question": "<p>\"The hold of the nationalist imagination on our colonial past is such that anything inadequately or improperly nationalist is just not history.\"<br><br>\nWhich of the following statements best reflects the author's opinion? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Nationalists are highly imaginative.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>History is viewed through the filter of nationalism.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Our colonial past never happened.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Nationalism has to be both adequately and properly imagined.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>History is viewed through the filter of nationalism.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118409/gate-cse-2017-set-1-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 47,
          "question": "<p>Research in the workplace reveals that people work for many reasons _______________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>money beside</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>beside money</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>money besides</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>besides money</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>besides money</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118405/gate-cse-2017-set-1-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 48,
          "question": "<p>After Rajendra Chola returned from his voyage to Indonesia, he ________ to visit the temple in Thanjavur. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>was wishing</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is wishing</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>wished</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>had wished</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>wished</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118403/gate-cse-2017-set-1-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 49,
          "question": "<p>All hill-stations have a lake. Ooty has two lakes.<br>\n<br>\nWhich of the statement(s) below is/are logically valid and can be inferred from the above sentences?\n<br><br>\n(i).   Ooty is not a hill-station.\n<br>(ii).  No hill-station can have more than one lake. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) only.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(ii) only.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both (i) and (ii)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39534/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-08#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 50,
          "question": "<p>Computers were invented for performing only high-end useful computations. However, it is no understatement that they have taken over our world today. The internet, for example, is ubiquitous. Many believe that the internet itself is an unintended consequence of the original invention. With the advent of mobile computing on our phones, a whole new dimension is now enabled. One is left wondering if all these developments are good or, more importantly, required.<br><br>Which of the statement(s) below is/are logically valid and can be inferred from the above paragraph?<br>(i) The author believes that computers are not good for us.\n<br>\n(ii) Mobile computers and the internet are both intended inventions. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(ii) only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both (i) and (ii)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39533/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-07#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 51,
          "question": "<p>Pick the odd one from the following options. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>CADBE</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>JHKIL</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>XVYWZ</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>ONPMQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>ONPMQ</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39528/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-04#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 52,
          "question": "<p>Find the odd one in the following group of words.\n<br><br>\nmock, deride, praise, jeer <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mock</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Deride</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Praise</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Jeer</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Praise</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39530/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-03#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 53,
          "question": "<p>Nobody knows how the Indian cricket team is going to cope with the difficult and seamer-friendly wickets in Australia.\n<br><br>\nChoose the option which is closest in meaning to the underlined phrase in the above sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Put up with.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Put in with.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Put down to.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Put up against.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Put up with.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39531/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-02#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 54,
          "question": "<p>The man who is now Municipal Commissioner worked as _____________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the security guard at a university</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a security guard at the university</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a security guard at university</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>the security guard at the university</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>a security guard at the university</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39529/gate-cse-2016-set-2-question-ga-01#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 55,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements relating to the level of poker play of four players P, Q, R and S.<br><br>I.    P always beats Q<br>\nII.   R always beats S<br>\nIII.  S loses to P only sometimes.<br>\nIV.  R always loses to Q<br><br>\nWhich of the following can be logically inferred from the above statements?<br><br>(i).  P is likely to beat all the three other players\n<br>(ii).  S is the absolute worst player in the set <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(ii) only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) and (ii) only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>neither (i) nor (ii)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>neither (i) nor (ii)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39617/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga08#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 56,
          "question": "<p>Indian currency notes show the denomination indicated in at least seventeen languages. If this is not an indication of the nation's diversity, nothing else is.\n<br><br>\nWhich of the following can be logically inferred from the above sentences? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>India is a country of exactly seventeen languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Linguistic pluralism is the only indicator of a nation's diversity.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Indian currency notes have sufficient space for all the Indian languages.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Linguistic pluralism is strong evidence of India's diversity.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Linguistic pluralism is strong evidence of India's diversity.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39613/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga07#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 57,
          "question": "<p>If 'relftaga' means carefree, 'otaga' means careful and 'fertaga' means careless, which of the following could mean 'aftercare'? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>zentaga</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>tagafer</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>tagazen</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>relffer</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>tagazen</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39609/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga04#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 58,
          "question": "<p>Archimedes said, \"Give me a lever long enough and a fulcrum on which to place it, and I will move the world.\"\n<br><br>\nThe sentence above is an example of a ____________ statement. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>figurative</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>collateral</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>literal</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>figurine</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>figurative</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39606/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga03#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 59,
          "question": "<p>rewording of something written or spoken is a __________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>paraphrase</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>paradox</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>paradigm</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>paraffin</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>paraphrase</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39607/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga02#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 60,
          "question": "<p>Out of the following four sentences, select the most suitable sentence with respect to grammar and usage. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I will not leave the place until the minister does not meet me.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I will not leave the place until the minister doesn't meet me.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I will not leave the place until the minister meet me.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I will not leave the place until the minister meets me.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I will not leave the place until the minister meets me.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39608/gate-cse-2016-set-1-question-ga01#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 61,
          "question": "<p>Most experts feel that in spite of possessing all the technical skills required to be a batsman of the highest order, he is unlikely to be so due to lack of requisite temperament. He was guilty of throwing away his wicket several time after working hard to lay a strong foundation. His critics pointed out that until he addressed his problem, success at the highest level will continue to elude him. <br>Which of the statement(s) below is/are logically valid and can be inferred from the above passage?\n<br><br>i.   He was already a successful batsman at the highest level.\n<br>ii.  He was to improve his temperament in order to become a great batsman.\n<br>iii. He failed to make many of his good starts count.\n<br>iv.  Improving his technical skills will guarantee success. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>iii and iv</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>ii and iii</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>i, ii and iii</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>ii only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>ii and iii</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"#a_list\" target=\"_blank&quot;\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 62,
          "question": "<p>Alexander turned his attention towards India, since he had conquered Persia.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the statements below is logically valid and can be inferred from the above sentence? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Alexander would not have turned his attention towards India had he not conquered Persia.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Alexander was not ready to rest on his laurels, and wanted to march to India.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Alexander was not completely in control of his army and could command it to move towards India.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Since Alexander's kingdom extended to Indian borders after the conquest of Persia, he was keen to move further.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Alexander would not have turned his attention towards India had he not conquered Persia.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8306/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 63,
          "question": "<p>Select the pair of best expresses a relationship similar to that expressed in the pair:\n<br><br>\nChildren : Pediatrician <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Adult : Orthopaedist</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Females : Gynaecologist</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Kidney : Nephrologist</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Skin : Dermatologist</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Females : Gynaecologist</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8302/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 64,
          "question": "<p>Extreme focus on syllabus and studying for tests has become such a dominant concern of Indian student that they close their minds to anything ___________ to the requirements of the exam. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>related</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>extraneous</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>outside</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>useful</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>extraneous</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8301/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 65,
          "question": "<p>The Tamil version of __________ John Abraham-starrer Madras Cafe __________ cleared by the Censor Board with no cuts last week, but the film's distributor _______ no takers among the exhibitors for a release in Tamilnadu _______ this Friday. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mr., was, found, on</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a, was, found, at</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>the, was, found, on</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a, being, find at</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>the, was, found, on</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8300/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 66,
          "question": "<p>If ROAD is written as URDG, then SWANshould be written as: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>VXDQ</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>VZDQ</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>VZDP</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>UXDQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>VZDQ</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8298/gate-cse-2015-set-3-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 67,
          "question": "<p>Out of the following 4 sentences, select the most suitable sentence with respect to grammar and usage: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it was of no use to them.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The report was useless to them because there were no needed information in it.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Since the report did not contain the needed information, it was not real useful to them.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it would not had been useful to them.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Since the report lacked needed information, it was of no use to them.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8041/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-10#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 68,
          "question": "<p>A generic term that includes various items of clothing such as a skirt, a pair of trousers and a shirt is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fabric</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>textile</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fiber</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>apparel</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>apparel</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8032/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 69,
          "question": "<p>Choose the statement where underlined word is used correctly. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The industrialist had a \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel }}\\) jet.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I write my experience in my \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel }}\\) diary.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) are being given the day off.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Being religious is a  \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) aspect.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>All \\(\\underline{ \\text{personnel} }\\) are being given the day off.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8029/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 70,
          "question": "<p>We __________ our friends's birthday and we _________ how to make it up to him. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>completely forgot --- don't just know</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>forgot completely ---don't just know</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>completely forgot --- just don't know</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>forgot completely --- just don't know</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>completely forgot --- just don't know</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8028/gate-cse-2015-set-2-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 71,
          "question": "<p>The given statement is followed by some courses of action. Assuming the statement to be true, decide the correct option.\n<br><br>\nStatement:\n<br>\nThere has been a significant drop in the water level in the lakes supplying water to the city.\n<br><br>\nCourse of action:\n<br>\nI.   The water supply authority should impose a partial cut in supply to tackle the situation.\n<br>II.  The government should appeal to all the residents through mass media for minimal use of water.\n<br>III. The government should ban the water supply in lower areas. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Statements I and II follow.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Statements I and III follow.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Statements II and III follow.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All the statements follow.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Statements I and II follow.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8012/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-8#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 72,
          "question": "<p>Select the alternative meaning of the underlined part of the sentence.\n<br>\nThe chain snatchers \\(\\underline{\\text{took to their heels}}\\) when the police party arrived. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Took shelter in a thick jungle</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Open indiscriminate fire</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Took to flight</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Unconditionally surrendered</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Took to flight</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8011/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-7#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 73,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following combinations is incorrect? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Acquiescence - Submission</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Wheedle - Roundabout</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Flippancy - Lightness</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Profligate - Extravagant</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Wheedle - Roundabout</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8008/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-5#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 74,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following options is the closest in meaning of the sentence below?\n<br><br>\nShe enjoyed herself immensely at the party. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>She had a terrible time at the party</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>She had a horrible time at the party</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>She had a terrific time at the party</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>She had a terrifying time at the party</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>She had a terrific time at the party</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8003/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 75,
          "question": "<p>Didn't you buy ____ when you went shopping? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>any paper</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>much paper</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>no paper</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a few paper</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>any paper</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/7995/gate-cse-2015-set-1-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 76,
          "question": "<p>By the beginning of the 20th century, several hypotheses were being proposed, suggesting a paradigm shift in our understanding of the universe. However, the clinching evidence was provided by experimental measurements of the position of a star which was directly behind our sun.\n<br><br>\nWhich of the following inference(s) may be drawn from the above passage? <br><br>i.   Our understanding of the universe changes based on the positions of stars\n<br>ii.  Paradigm shifts usually occur at the beginning of centuries\n<br>iii. Stars are important objects in the universe\n<br>iv.  Experimental evidence was important in confirming this paradigm shift <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>i, ii and iv</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>iii only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>i and iv</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>iv only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>iv only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2031/gate-cse-2014-set-3-question-ga-7#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 77,
          "question": "<p>Choose the word that is opposite in meaning to the word \"coherent\". <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>sticky</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>well-connected</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>rambling</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>friendly</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>rambling</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2026/gate-cse-2014-set-3-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 78,
          "question": "<p>If she _______ how to calibrate the instrument, she ________ done the experiment. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>knows, will have</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>knew, had</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>had known, could have</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>should have known, would have</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>had known, could have</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2025/gate-cse-2014-set-3-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 79,
          "question": "<p>\\(\\underset{\\text{I}}{\\underline{\\text{While trying to collect}}}\\) an envelope \\(\\underset{\\text{II}}{\\underline{\\text{from under the table}}}\\),<br> \\(\\underset{\\text{III}}{\\underline{\\text{Mr. X fell down}}}\\) and \\(\\underset{\\text{IV}}{\\underline{\\text{was losing consciousness}}}\\).<br><br>Which one of the above underlined parts of the sentence is NOT appropriate? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>IV</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2024/gate-cse-2014-set-3-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 80,
          "question": "<p>Number of people diagnosed with dengue fever (contracted from the bite of a mosquito) in North India is twice the number diagnosed last year. Municipal authorities have concluded that measures to control the mosquito population have failed in this region.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements, if true, does not contradict this conclusion? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A high proportion of the affected population has returned from neighbouring countries where dengue is prevalent</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>More cases of dengue are now reported because of an increase in the Municipal Office's administrative efficiency</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Many more cases of dengue are being diagnosed this year since the introduction of a new and effective diagnostic test</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The number of people with malarial fever (also contracted from mosquito bites) has increased this year</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>The number of people with malarial fever (also contracted from mosquito bites) has increased this year</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1944/gate-cse-2014-set-2-question-ga-7#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 81,
          "question": "<p>The old city of Koenigsberg, which had a German majority population before World War 2, is now called Kaliningrad. After the events of the war, Kaliningrad is now a Russian territory and has a predominantly Russian population. It is bordered by the Baltic Sea on the north and the countries of Poland to the south and west and Lithuania to the east respectively. Which of the statements below can be inferred from this passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Kaliningrad was historically Russian in its ethnic make up</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Kaliningrad is a part of Russia despite it not being contiguous with the rest of Russia</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Koenigsberg was renamed Kaliningrad, as that was its original Russian name</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Poland and Lithuania are on the route from Kaliningrad to the rest of Russia</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Kaliningrad is a part of Russia despite it not being contiguous with the rest of Russia</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1943/gate-cse-2014-set-2-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 82,
          "question": "<p>Match the columns.\n<br><br>\\(\\begin{array}{ll|ll}\\hline &amp;\\textbf{Column 1} &amp; &amp; \\textbf{Column 2 } \\\\\\hline 1.&amp; \\text{eradicate} &amp;P. &amp;\\text{misrepresent}\\\\\\hline 2.&amp;\\text{distort} &amp;Q.&amp; \\text{soak completely}\\\\\\hline 3.&amp;\\text{saturate} &amp;R.&amp; \\text{use}\\\\\\hline 4.&amp;\\text{utilize} &amp;S.&amp; \\text{destroy utterly}\\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1:S, 2:P, 3:Q, 4:R</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1:P, 2:Q, 3:R, 4:S</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1:Q, 2:R, 3:S, 4:P</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1:S, 2:P, 3:R, 4:Q</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1:S, 2:P, 3:Q, 4:R</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1940/gate-cse-2014-set-2-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 83,
          "question": "<p>Who ___________ was coming to see us this evening? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>you said</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>did you say</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>did you say that</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>had you said</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>did you say</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1939/gate-cse-2014-set-2-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 84,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate phrase from the options given below to complete the following sentence.\n<br><br>\nIndia is a post-colonial country because <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>it was a former British colony</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Indian Information Technology professionals have colonized the world</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>India does not follow any colonial practices</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>India has helped other countries gain freedom</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>it was a former British colony</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1938/gate-cse-2014-set-2-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 85,
          "question": "<p>Geneticists say that they are very close to confirming the genetic roots of psychiatric illnesses such as depression and schizophrenia, and consequently, that doctors will be able to eradicate these diseases through early identification and gene therapy.\n<br><br>\nOn which of the following assumptions does the statement above rely?\n<br>\nSelect one: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Strategies are now available for eliminating psychiatric illnesses</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Certain psychiatric illnesses have a genetic basis</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All human diseases can be traced back to genes and how they are expressed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>In the future, genetics will become the only relevant field for identifying psychiatric illnesses</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Certain psychiatric illnesses have a genetic basis</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/775/gate-cse-2014-set-1-question-ga-7#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 86,
          "question": "<p>The Palghat Gap (or Palakkad Gap) , a region about 30 km wide in the southern part of the Western Ghats in India, is lower than the hilly terrain to its north and south. The exact reasons for the formation of this gap are not clear. It results in the neighbouring regions of Tamil Nadu getting more rainfall from the South West monsoon and the neighbouring regions of Kerala having higher summer temperatures.\n<br><br>\nWhat can be inferred from this passage?\n<br>\nSelect one: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The Palghat gap is caused by high rainfall and high temperatures in southern Tamil Nadu and Kerala</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The regions in Tamil Nadu and Kerala that are near the Palghat Gap are low-lying</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The low terrain of the Palghat Gap has a significant impact on weather patterns in neighbouring parts of Tamil Nadu and Kerala</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Higher summer temperatures result in higher rainfall near the Palghat Gap area</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The low terrain of the Palghat Gap has a significant impact on weather patterns in neighbouring parts of Tamil Nadu and Kerala</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/774/gate-cse-2014-set-1-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 87,
          "question": "<p>In a press meet on the recent scam, the minister said, \"The buck stops here\". What did the minister convey by the statement? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>He wants all the money</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>He will return the money</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>He will assume final responsibility</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>He will resist all enquiries</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>He will assume final responsibility</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/772/gate-cse-2014-set-1-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 88,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate word from the options given below to complete the following sentence.\n<br><br>\nHe could not understand the judges awarding her the first prize, because he thought that her performance was quite _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>superb</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>medium</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>mediocre</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>exhilarating</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>mediocre</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/771/gate-cse-2014-set-1-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 89,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following options is the closest in meaning to the phrase in bold in the\nsentence below?<br><br>It is fascinating to see life forms **cope with** varied environmental conditions. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Adopt to</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Adapt to</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Adept in</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Accept with</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Adapt to</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/56/gate-cse-2014-set-1-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 90,
          "question": "<p>After several defeats in wars, Robert Bruce went in exile and wanted to commit suicide. Just before committing suicide, he came across a spider attempting tirelessly to have its net. Time and again, the spider failed but that did not deter it to refrain from making attempts. Such attempts by the spider made Bruce curious. Thus, Bruce started observing the near-impossible goal of the spider to have the net. Ultimately, the spider succeeded in having its net despite several failures. Such act of the spider encouraged Bruce not to commit suicide. And then, Bruce went back again and won many a battle, and the rest is history.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following assertions is best supported by the above information? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Failure is the pillar of success.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Honesty is the best policy.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Life begins and ends with adventures.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>No adversity justifies giving up hope.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>No adversity justifies giving up hope.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1567/gate-cse-2013-question-63#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 91,
          "question": "<p>Choose the grammatically INCORRECT sentence: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>He is of Asian origin.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>They belonged to Africa.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>She is an European.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>They migrated from India to Australia.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>She is an European.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1564/gate-cse-2013-question-60#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 92,
          "question": "<p>Were you a bird, you ______ in the sky. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>would fly</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>shall fly</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>should fly</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>shall have flown</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>would fly</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1563/gate-cse-2013-question-59#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 93,
          "question": "<p>Complete the sentence:\n<br><br>\nUniversalism is to particularism as diffuseness is to ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>specificity</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>neutrality</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>generality</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>adaptation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>specificity</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1560/gate-cse-2013-question-57#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 94,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following options is the closest in meaning to the word given below?<br><br>\nNadir <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Highest</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Lowest</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Medium</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Integration</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Lowest</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1559/gate-cse-2013-question-56#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 95,
          "question": "<p>Wanted Temporary, Part-time persons for the post of Field Interviewer to conduct personal interviews to collect and collate economic data. Requirements: High School-pass, must be available for Day, Evening and Saturday work. Transportation paid, expenses reimbursed.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following is the best inference from the above advertisement? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Gender-discriminatory</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Xenophobic</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Not designed to make the post attractive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Not gender-discriminatory</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Not gender-discriminatory</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2209/gate-cse-2012-question-61#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 96,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate alternative from the options given below to complete the following sentence:\n<br><br>\nSuresh's dog is the one ________ was hurt in the stampede. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>that</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>which</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>who</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>whom</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>that</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2200/gate-cse-2012-question-60#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 97,
          "question": "<p>Choose the grammatically INCORRECT sentence: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>They gave us the money back less the service charges of Three Hundred rupees.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>This country's expenditure is not less than that of Bangladesh.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The committee initially asked for a funding of Fifty Lakh rupees, but later settled for a lesser sum.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>This country's expenditure on educational reforms is very less.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>This country's expenditure on educational reforms is very less.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2198/gate-cse-2012-question-59#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 98,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following options is the closest in meaning to the word given below?\n<br><br>\nMitigate <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Diminish</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Divulge</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Dedicate</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Denote</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Diminish</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2197/gate-cse-2012-question-58#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 99,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate alternative from the options given below to complete the following sentence:\n<br><br>\nDespite several _________ the mission succeeded in its attempt to resolve the conflict. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>attempts</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>setbacks</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>meetings</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>delegations</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>setbacks</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2195/gate-cse-2012-question-57#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 100,
          "question": "<p>Few school curricula include a unit on how to deal with bereavement and grief, and\nyet all students at some point in their lives suffer from losses through death and parting.\n<br>\nBased on the above passage which topic would not be included in a unit on bereavement? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>how to write a letter of condolence</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>what emotional stages are passed through in the healing process</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>what the leading causes of death are</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>how to give support to a grieving friend</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>what the leading causes of death are</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2171/gate-cse-2011-question-61#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 101,
          "question": "<p>Choose the word from the options given below that is most nearly opposite in the meaning to the given word\n<br>\nAmalgamate <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>merge</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>split</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>collect</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>separate</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>separate</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2170/gate-cse-2011-question-60#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 102,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate word from the options given below to complete the following sentence.\n<br>\nIf you are trying to make a strong impression on your audience, you cannot do so by being understated, tentative or ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>hyperbolic</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>restrained</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>argumentative</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>indifferent</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>restrained</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2169/gate-cse-2011-question-59#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 103,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate word(s) from the options given below to complete the following sentence.\n<br>\nI contemplated _________ Singapore for my vacation but decided against it. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>to visit</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>having to visit</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>visiting</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>for a visit</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>visiting</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2167/gate-cse-2011-question-58#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 104,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following options is the closest in the meaning to the word below:\n<br>\nInexplicable <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Incomprehensible</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Indelible</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Inextricable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Infallible</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Incomprehensible</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2165/gate-cse-2011-question-56#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 105,
          "question": "<p>Modern warfare has changed from large scale clashes of armies to suppression of civilian populations. Chemical agents that do their work silently appear to be suited to such warfare; and regretfully, there exist people in military establishments who think that chemical agents are useful tools for their cause.\n<br><br>\nWhich of the following statements best sums up the meaning of the above passage: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Modern warfare has resulted in civil strife.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Chemical agents are useful in modern warfare.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Use of chemical agents in warfare would be undesirable.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>People in military establishments like to use chemical agents in war.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>People in military establishments like to use chemical agents in war.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2371/gate-cse-2010-question-63#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 106,
          "question": "<p>The question below consists of a pair of related words followed by four pairs of words. Select the pair that best expresses the relation in the original pair.\n<br>\nUnemployed : Worker <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fallow : land</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>unaware : sleeper</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>wit : jester</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>renovated : house</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>fallow : land</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2368/gate-cse-2010-question-60#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 107,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate word from the options given below to complete the following sentence:\n<br>\nIf we manage to __________ our natural resources, we would leave a better planet for our children. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>uphold</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>restrain</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>cherish</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>conserve</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>conserve</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2366/gate-cse-2010-question-58#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 108,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following options is the closest in meaning to the word given below:\n<br>\nCircuitous <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>cyclic</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>indirect</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>confusing</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>crooked</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>indirect</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2365/gate-cse-2010-question-57#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 109,
          "question": "<p>Choose the most appropriate word from the options given below to complete the following sentence:\n<br>\nHis rather casual remarks on politics ________ his lack of seriousness about the subject. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>masked</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>belied</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>betrayed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>suppressed</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>betrayed</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2364/gate-cse-2010-question-56#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
